What are you guys doing here?
So nice outside.
It's still the beginning of the semester.
I guess.
Maybe when we get closer to the end of the semester, there'll be fewer people.
Let's see.
OK, It's good that you're here.
I'm joking, of course, there will be better days in the future, both in class and also outside.
So, but at some point the class will end outside, will be there forever, hopefully, if we don't
destroy the world as human beings, which is quite possible.
OK, so today we're going to continue where we started last time, combinational logic.
Actually, we, we made a lot of progress on combinational logic.
We now know how to construct some circuits.
We're going to see some more.
Last time, just to jog your memory, we started with transistors as the basics and then we built
logic gates and then we built combinational components.
We're going to build some more combinational components today and then we're going to add memory to
it, which will take us to sequential logic.
Sounds good.
OK, just to jog your memory, this is what we discussed.
These are some readings, more readings.
This is what I said.
Just again to jog your memory, this is the beginning of the second, third lecture, which we're going
to cover.
Hopefully, we'll finish combination logic in the first half of the lecture today.
And this is what we had covered last time.
I think we discussed a lot of these, so I will not go into it except reminding you with some slides.
So this should all be familiar to you.
You should be very comfortable with AND OR not NAND NOR.
These are not NAND AND gates, and hopefully you have an idea of how this is constructed with the
abstraction of a transistor.
And then we built combination logic circuits.
We talked about Boolean logic equations.
We talked about how to use Boolean equations to represent a circuit, which was good and nice, and
we.
Boolean equations essentially enable us to specify the functional behaviour of a circuit and they
also enable us to methodically transform a function into simpler functions by reducing it to to
functions with smaller terms.
This is called logic simplification or Boolean simplification or logic minimisation.
And you can automate this process as we've discussed today at the end of the first half of the
lecture, we're going to talk a little bit more about automation.
And a lot of design process today is automated using computer aided design.
And essentially AI tools are also coming in significantly in electronic design automation.
But if you really want to build those AI tools and make them better, design better circuits, you'd
better understand how these logic is constructed.
And the reason we look at these things is because different Boolean expressions lead to different
logic gate implementations.
And they may have different area cost, different power, different latency, different energy
properties, depending on the underlying gates that are implemented using different kinds of
transistors or different ways of combining transistors.
So hopefully that's clear.
For example, a NAND gate may be much faster than an OR gate because the designer at the lower
abstraction level did something smart to make it much faster.
That's just an example, OK?
We've talked about the sum of products and product of sums forms, so people hopefully remember
these.
We're going to talk more about that when we talk about the full adder.
And we talked about logic simplification.
We're going to talk more about that.
Basically, you can represent any function using a truth table.
Truth table is basically all of the inputs, how all different input combinations lead to change the
output.
Essentially, you can specify a function fully and you can take that truth table and turn it into a
sum of products form or product of sums form.
We're going to do a little bit more of that, and today we're going to start with full one bit adder
after I cover the summary.
So we were discussing some combinational logic blocks used in modern computers.
Clearly there are gates.
These are simple basic common logic gates and we covered those and we covered decoder and
multiplexer today.
We're going to cover the blue parts until we finish the combinational logic lecture.
Sounds good.
So you're going to be able to do how to do, you're going to able to, you're going to be able to
design an adder very soon.
And if you design the adder, you can design A multiplier divider.
A lot of things we're not going to do multiplier and divider.
I'll leave that to your books if you're interested.
But once you design natter, you can do multiplication also, right?
Multiplication is shift and adds, and there are many algorithms that are used for multiplication.
OK.
So we're going to cover some interesting things, but again, just to jog your memory, we're going to
use decoders and multiplexers later, especially in sequential circuits decoders.
Decoder is an input pattern detector.
It has N inputs and two of the N outputs.
We covered this last time and only one of the outputs that is matching the input pattern is set to
1.
Everything else it's set to 0.
So this is one example of a 2 to 4 decoder.
For example, it detects whether the input pattern is 00011011 OK and this is going to be used when
we build memory soon.
For example, we're going to use a decoder to determine the address of a location that we're going to
read from.
OK, multiplexer is a selector.
Basically, it has multiple data inputs and one select input.
And depending on the value of the select input, it passes one of the data inputs to the output it
selects, essentially.
So this is an example of two to one multiplexer.
You can see the data inputs D, select input S, and that's it.
And we discussed how to implement it using logic gates in the past lecture.
Hopefully you guys remember all of this, right?
All good.
OK, we're almost at the end of the overview and this is another view of the multiplexer.
And we solved this problem that I assigned to you, which is how to design a four to one multiplexer
from 2:00 to 1:00.
Multiplexers.
Basically, you have a multiplexer tree that looks like this, and you can design an 8 to 1
multiplexer from more 4 to 1 multiplexers and you can keep going.
We'd also discussed logic using multiplexers, which is a lot of fun.
I'm not going to repeat that.
We discussed you can build look up tables using multiplexers, which you're going to see in Fpgas
when you program them.
It's fascinating basically.
So you're going to actually program real devices, real FPGA boards, chips that use all of the
concepts that we're discussing lots.
OK, I'm I'm going to skip that.
We also discussed logic using decoder.
So this is all last lecture.
Now we're caught up.
Hopefully all of the stuff is, and you're closer to your processor in the brain.
They're fetched from storage, which is far away, and now you're warmed up.
Now let's talk about some other logic blocks.
Full ladder.
I've kind of thrown this at you in the last lecture.
Let's take a look at how we would design a full ladder.
So this is binary edition, probably.
How many people have seen binary edition before?
OK, yeah, you've seen it in high school probably.
Essentially every bit is added to every other bit.
It's similar to a decimal edition.
You go from right to left, you do one column at a time, and when you add a zero to B0, you get 1 sum
bit and one carry bit.
Sum is a zero, carry bit is propagated to the next edition.
And then you add a 1B1C1 and you get the sum bit and a carry bit C2.
And you keep doing this basically.
So this can be a single bit edition is called a full adder, basically A0B 0C0.
Let's say, let's say there's a carry in you can you can actually generate the truth table of this
relatively easily.
I'm doing generate it for you.
But this could have been a problem that I gave to you, right?
Generate the truth table of a binary edition.
So there are three inputs AIBI carry I and then there are two outputs of the addition.
One is the sum I and the other is carry to the next bit, right?
So you can see that hopefully you can verify that this is true.
If if at least two of AIBI carry I are one, then carry I plus one should be 1.
You generate a carry if at least two of the inputs are one.
So that's a bitwise majority function we call it.
So if the majority of the inputs are 1, you get a one as part of the carry, right?
OK, let's do this.
OK, and and the sum.
The sum is actually something else.
Sum is really an XOR function of the three inputs.
If the if an odd number of inputs is 1, you get a one in the sum.
And again you can verify that on your own.
So that's my thinking based representation, but I don't need to think also which is good.
You can actually automate these by taking this truth table and generating a sum of products form.
And this is the sum of product form.
You remember sum of product form.
You look at basically this function of three inputs and two outputs.
3 inputs means there are 8 min terms marked with small M0 to M7 and we look at 2 outputs.
We look at if you want to generate the carry one.
If you want to write carry one in sum of product form, carry I plus one.
Sorry.
You look at all the places where carry I plus one is 1.
The result is 1.
Basically the result of the function is 1 and basically you find out the minterms for that.
So carry I plus one is 1 if minterm 0123 is true or if minterm 5 is true, or if minterm 6 is true or
if midterm 7 is true.
So carry I plus one can be written that way, in other words.
Carry I plus one is 1 I can I can express carry I plus one as AI bar BI carry I or AIBI bar carry I
or AIBI carry I bar or AIBI carry I and that's what's shown over here.
So this particular circuit over here shows all the midterms.
If you look at this, there are 8 gates over here, 83 inputs and gates and each of them correspond to
1 minterm of the truth table and I can actually put them.
I can create a circuit that looks like this which is great and connect them to an OR gate but
connect the right outputs right minterms to the OR gate for which I know the function will be 1.
So this is the carry I plus one where the minterms that make carry I +11 are connected to this OR
gate.
So some of products form at least to two level logic where you can generate all of them in terms
with and gates and then all the appropriate ones that lead to one in the output.
Hopefully that makes sense, right.
It's a beautiful representation as you can see.
Yes, that's the carry bit.
Basically you, you add 2 bits, you get a sum and then you get a carry over to the next digit, right?
Makes sense, right.
Basically it's addition.
OK, so sum is similar.
You can see that the sum is.
You can express the sum as sum of min terms M1M2.
What is this?
I guess M4 and M7 right?
There are 4 min terms that need to be connected to this or gate to make someone connect the
appropriate ones.
I'm not going to check the accuracy of the correctness accuracy of the connections, but they're
accurate in this particular case.
So just by I didn't think here right at all.
I just represented took the truth table and mapped it to a circuit that generates all of the
minterms and I connected the appropriate minterms to the OR gate that would or those minterms and
give me the carry carry I plus one bit and some I bit, which is good.
This I can automate this process.
That's the beauty of this, right?
OK, so this is the full adder right now and I can represent this as a module.
There is some implementation underneath.
I can forget about it.
Of course, it's not an optimised implementation.
If you're now, you can go ahead and minimise all of these either using Boolean logic equations or
using some other techniques that we will discuss later on.
And if you actually minimise it, you'll find out that's the majority function and it's an XOR
function like we discussed.
And you can actually build the circuit in a much simpler way.
It makes sense, right?
So what I've shown you is a universal technique to create any circuit from a truth table sum of
products form.
That was the reason why we actually started with that.
But I can simplify it now.
Assume that we optimise the full adder in some way, which is essentially majority in XOR gates.
You can design bigger adders.
So this was a one bit adder.
If you want to do 4 bit addition, you can create essentially we want to add 2 four bit numbers A&B.
You can use the full adders we've used earlier, we've created with some optimised implementation.
So this is 1 bit addition, A0B0 some zero and carrying is 0 because this is the first bit, there is
no carry that comes from the previous digit.
And then you generate a carry to the next full adder and then you add a 1B1 and carry one and then
some one.
And that generates a carry to the next bit and then to the next bit to the next bit.
So this way you can generate, you can create any N bit adder.
In this particular case, N is equal to 4 by rippling the carry.
It's called ripple carry adder.
This is called the ripple carry adder.
What you do is really operate on one bit at a time, but the carry is rippled to the next stage, next
bit.
So this is what we're doing essentially, it's a sequential process, right?
This is what you do when you actually do the binary edition also Sounds good, right?
Hopefully this is all clear and beautiful.
OK, so this is a circuit that can do 4 bit addition.
You can create a circuit that can do 32 bit edition, binary edition, 64 bit, 128 bit.
The downside is basically now you need to in order for the latest full adder to operate.
It's a sequential process, right?
All of the adders should generate their carries beforehand.
So we didn't talk about timing yet, but there's a timing issue in the end.
We're going to talk more about timing.
But you can think about serial processing, right?
You're serially processing every bit the, the, the full adder generates its final results.
The full adder that's at the most significant bit over here generates its final result only after
the previous full adder generates its carry carry into the last bit, and this generates its final.
Result which is carry over here only after it gets C2.
This generates its final result only after it gets C 1.
So it's a serial process which is not good and people don't want these ripple carry adders if you're
doing 64 bit edition for example.
That's why people optimise their adders.
So this is the ripple carry adder from your book.
It's the same thing.
Basically.
This is the description or symbol for an adder.
This is another adder.
This is called a carry look ahead adder, which I'm not going to go into detail, but I'm going to
mention it.
If you're interested, you can read your book.
I'm not going to ask you questions about either, but this is just one example of an optimised adder.
And you can see that what this adder does is it does 4 bit carry look ahead adder block over here.
Inside each block, there is a four bit ripple carry adder.
These people made the decision, These designers made the decision that oh, I can tolerate the
latency of a four bit carry chain.
Let's say it's called the carry chain and the carry out from this block is not generated as the
output of the four bit ripple carry outer.
But they have some specialised logic which I'll let you read from your book that is just there to
generate the carries for the next block.
So this specialised logic is something that you, the designer, used special Boolean equations for so
that you can generate this C3 very quickly so that this other adder can get C3 earlier.
Similarly, this adder has a specialised logic that can generate C7 very quickly so that the next
adder can get C7 quickly and you can get, you get the idea.
So basically what we're doing is we're decoupling the generation of the four sums from the
generation of the last carry.
We have specialised logic to do the carry generation so that that can go very fast hopefully.
And we have ripple carry adder like before to do the sum generation for for four bit.
Now of course there's a trade off over here.
The area increases, right?
You don't just have a four bit ripple carry adder over here.
You also have a lot of gates over here to generate the carry fast.
Even though the carry is already generated over here, you're not using it because that's very slow.
This is the specialised logic that generates C3.
We ignore the C3 that comes out of here.
Sounds interesting, right?
This is a very.
So there's a bigger principle over here, which is if you want to speed up processing, you can.
There are two things actually, 2 principles.
If you want to speed up processing, find what limits you in terms of time and do it quickly.
How do you do it quickly?
Design very specialised logic to do it quickly as opposed to more general purpose logic which is the
top ripple carrier.
The second thing is you need more area for that.
So there is a very fundamental trade off between latency and area.
Hardware cost usually, almost always actually if you want to improve speed you need to spend more
area and that's a great example of spending more area to improve speed.
Now the beauty is we have a lot of transistors today.
If you want to improve speed, you can use some of them to improve speed.
OK, I spent some time on this because it's really principles.
Even though you may not exactly know how this carry is generated, but some of you may be interested
in designing the circuitry to generate only the carry, right?
What you will need to do to generate that is figure out how to basically do a truth table only for
the carry out C3 and express it in terms of all of A0B0.
Well, whatever all of these inputs are.
So basically your output, the output of this function is CC-3 and inputs are C in A0B0A1B1A2B2A3B3.
You don't care about any of the intermediate CS, you don't care about the s s.
The only thing you want is C3.
And that's how you, you generate the truth table.
You specialize that logic and you can do sum of products forms and then you can reduce that using
Boolean equations.
Sounds good, right?
So you can, there's no magic you can see here, right?
It's it's really you need to figure out what you want to build and what you want to optimise.
If I didn't want to optimise the carry generation, I'd be happy with a ripple carry adder that looks
like this.
OK, OK, now let's jump into yes, there's a question.
Is there a convention?
No, they can go either way.
In this particular case, I'm using the convention that your book uses.
They go from right to left, but whenever you're designing, you can go from left to right and also
right to left.
You can do a snake thing.
OK, OK, yeah, there's no convention basically for that, but we will see there are other conventions
later on.
Not today.
OK, So yes.
Oh yeah.
For the previous slides, the latency mainly affected by the length of the wire or the.
Yeah, we'll talk about that later on.
Timing and verification both.
Basically the short answer is both how many gates you go through and how long the wires are.
They're all important.
OK, good questions.
So program by logic array.
Basically, I've given you this idea.
This is a general universal universal combinational logic structure that can implement essentially
any any N input M output function.
So sum of product form leads to two level logic.
We've seen that with full adder, we we see it with this sort of example and APLA program, a logic
array enables 2 level SOP implementation sum of products implementation of any N input M output
function.
So basically imagine that this you have the structure which we kind of had earlier, right?
You have 3 inputs and then min terms corresponding to three inputs and then in this particular case
3 outputs and then OR gates where any of the midterms can be connected to any of the inputs, 8
inputs of the OR gates and.
You assume that you can program this these connections.
Then you can implement any three input and a maximum 3 output function or maximum three input and
maximum 3 output function, let's say.
So you have an array of AND gates as you can see, followed by an array of OR gates AND gates.
Essentially the minimum, the number of possible min terms is the number of AND gates.
For an M AND input logic function you need you need 2 to the N and input AND gates and the number of
OR gates is dependent on the number of output columns in the truth table.
So if you want to implement the logic function, connect the output of an AND gate to the input of an
OR gate if the corresponding min terms include in the sum of product form of the function.
And that's kind of what we did actually when we constructed the other, but not exactly this way.
So this is basically a simple programmable logic construct.
I didn't show how the connections are implemented.
You can actually implement it yourself with what you have seen so far, but we're not going to go
into exactly how they're implemented with multiplexers.
You can implement the connections.
Basically assume that these are all programmable.
You program the connections from the AND gate outputs to the to the OR gate inputs to implement any
desired logic function.
I'm going to show you some more examples of this.
So there's other type of programmable logic also, which is an FPGA which you're going to use.
They're not going to use these PL.
as they could use the PL.
as all the FPGA use a lot of PL.
as actually, but newer ones use.
Look up tables and you'll see it in the labs.
Let's take a look at this full adder using APLA.
So we actually implemented this earlier.
This is the truth table of the full adder that you have seen earlier.
And essentially this is what we did with the PLA.
So what if you have some pro gamble connections over here, What you do is you figure out the
essentially which of the midterms you should connect to which of the OR gates, right?
For the, for example, if maybe, maybe I should go actually with the sum over here.
So for the sum to construct the sum for this to be 1, the min terms M1M2M5, sorry, M4 and M7 should
be connected over here.
So you program the connections.
I said those min terms are actually routed over here.
Hopefully that makes sense, right?
I'm going to show you another example over here.
So this input, for example, is not connected to any output.
So internally inside this structure, you don't connect this min term to any of the outputs because
you can see that this is the midterm 0 and no output is 1 for midterm 0.
So this output in the PLA doesn't get this.
This midterm doesn't get connected to any of the outputs and you do not need this output also.
So if you had APLA with three inputs and three outputs for to construct a full ladder, this output
is not used.
You don't connect anything to it.
Hopefully that makes sense, right.
OK, so this is your PLA basically, except I don't show you how to program it.
I'll leave that to you.
But with multiplexers you can do it.
With fuses you can do it.
There are many ways of designing it.
PLA we'll actually see soon.
tri-state buffers, you can actually use tri-state buffers.
You can use some fancy pass transistors, which we're not going to talk about, but your book talks a
little bit about.
So basically this is your PLA.
You have M inputs, P outputs and an and array and an or array and you can have midterms or
implicants.
Remember midterms are midterms are essentially rows of the truth table.
You need to have two to the north of them.
Implicants are not necessarily midterms, but they could actually.
For example, ABC is a midterm.
Three, input function AB is an implicant.
Don't worry about the terminology, I defined it in the last lecture, but it's not that important.
So you can actually optimise the PLA as well.
That's what I'm getting at.
And this is another PLA example from your other book, Harris and Harris.
You can take a look at it.
OK, hopefully that's clear.
Essentially, PLA is a direct programmable implementation of a sum of products form.
It could be the product of sums for them also, But you know that sum of products and product of sums
are essentially the same thing that's in quotation marks because they're not the same thing.
You know that sum of products is the De Morgan of the inverse of product of sums.
You know De Morgan's law, so you know exactly what they are now.
OK, so this brings us the logical completeness.
Basically, I've shown you a universal mechanism where you can implement anything, any function,
right?
You only need AND gates or gates and inverters and a way of connecting them to each other.
That's it.
So this is actually important for a theoretical study of circuits.
Any logic function we wish to implement could be accomplished with APLA, and it consists of only AND
gates or gates and inverters.
We just need to be able to route or program connections based on the SOT sum of products of the
intended logic function.
And why do I, why can why can we implement any function?
Because any function can be expressed as sum of products form, right?
Which means that the set of gates and or not is logically complete.
Because we can build a circuit to carry out the specification of any truth table without using any
other kind of gate.
This is very powerful, right?
That's logically logical completeness.
Now it turns out NAND is also logically complete.
You don't need AND OR NOT gates.
Only with NAND.
You can do it.
I'll let you think about it and prove it.
It's fun.
So the only thing that you need is NAND gates and a way of connecting them.
NOR is also logically complete.
So you can build anything using only NOR gates.
This is fun.
So your task is to prove this and this is something that I'm not going to do for you, but it's not
that hard.
You can take and you can, you can take that PLA form for example, and try to build it only with NAND
gates by converting gates to each other using Boolean logic equations.
Fun to do.
OK, any questions?
So this realisation actually is very interesting, right?
You can build anything that we build computers with using NAND and I'm going to show you how to do
that with how to rebuild memories also soon just with NAND gates.
OK.
But before we go through that, let's go through some more combinational blocks.
This is some more reading.
I say required readings, but if you understand everything very well in lectures and if you, if you
can do the exercise very well, in my opinion, you don't have to do the readings, but always we're
doing the readings is good to reinforce what you've learnt.
But if you're also interested in learning more about other components like multiplier, how do you
design A multiplier?
How do you design A divider?
How do you design A shifter rotator?
It's good to look at some of these chapters because I cannot go through every single block, right?
How do you do a square root approximation, for example?
There are a lot of interesting things out there, especially computer arithmetic is a huge field.
People that teach courses on computer arithmetic, how to do multiplication efficiently, for example,
that's really important today.
We're not going to go into that in this course, we don't have time, but comparator is important.
So I'm going to talk about comparator and it's also simple equality checker.
We're going to use this a lot in different parts of a computer.
Basically you check if 2 N input values are exactly the same bit twice, every bit is the same 2
input.
If 2 N input values are same, if every bit of the two inputs is the same, so 4 bit comparator.
So we're going to compare a four bit value A to a four bit value B.
If every bit like a zero is the same as B0A1 is the same as BBB, one AI is the same as BI.
For every I you get equal set, equal output set to 1.
Otherwise you get equal output set to 0.
So XOR gate and XOR gate is a comparator.
So we're going to use XOR gates, in this case XOR gates, because XOR gates the output of an XOR gate
is 1 if the two inputs 2 one bit inputs are not equal, right?
Makes sense in this case if a three and B3 are not equal.
You'll get a zero at the end because this is X NOR and if any of these X nor's lead to a zero, the
equals output will be 0.
Only if all of the X nor results are one, the equals one.
For all of the outputs of the X nor gates to be one, a three should every AI should be equal to BI,
right?
So this is your comparator, 4 bit comparator.
Now we're going to use them later when we do auto order execution, for example.
Sounds good, right?
This is one way of constructing the comparator.
You could you could construct in some other ways.
Again, you could take you could do the truth table of this function.
It's an 8 input 1 output function.
And you could do sum of products form that'll be a huge sum of products form, right?
Two to the 8 is 256.
So you'll have 256 and gates and one or gate and that will be PLA implementation, programmable logic
area implementation of an equality checker.
I didn't do that because it's quite expensive, right?
I did something else.
OK, so you have a lot of flexibility in design.
Doing the right thing is important if you want to actually minimise logic.
OK, now you know how to do the right thing.
Well, right thing depends on your goals, right?
Trade-offs.
In the end, if, if your, if your goal is to design something efficient, then you should be careful
how you minimise your circuit.
OK, it's good to ask the question, is this the minimal circuit?
But I'll let you think about that.
Also, is this the minimal circuit for any quality checker?
OK, I'll let you think.
OK, let's talk about arithmetic logic unit.
There's another component that's really important in the future because this is what actually does
the computation.
It's essentially a combination of functions.
Basically this unit combines a variety of arithmetic and logical operations into a single unit, and
it can perform only one function at a time in its simplest form.
So we call this alu.
So whenever you see alu, it's this basically.
So usually it's denoted with this symbol.
It doesn't, It looks like an adder, but it's not just an adder.
Basically you have an MN input data input A, another N input data input B, and a function input 3
bit function input, in this particular case F, and then a data output Y.
The function input determines what kind of function you are performing at the at this current time
on A&B.
So let's take a look at a particular ALU design.
The designer decided that if the function is 000, the function input is 000.
The output Y should be the bitwise AND of A&B if, if, If F is 001, the output should be A or B if F
is 010.
This arithmetic logic unit computes the addition, bitwise addition, bitwise binary addition of A&B.
Not to be confused with OR.
In this case, this is not used.
Somehow the designer decided that this was not used.
Fine, you can see that maybe in the future they're going to use it, right?
And you can, you can see the rest.
This is set less than.
So if the function is 111, the the arithmetic logic units computes whether a is less than B and the
outputs one if that's true.
Otherwise it outputs 0.
And then there's a subtraction also over here.
Sounds good, right?
So somebody specifies this and then gives you the symbol and then you can implement it.
And this is 1 implementation, one particular implementation of that specification makes sense,
right?
OK, I'll let you study it.
Yes, yeah, yes, yeah.
It's an overflow condition, for example.
That's they're special conditions.
We didn't cover it, but yes, if, if you have a carry and if you cannot represent it in the given
bits, that's called an overflow.
And usually the ALU outputs an overflow bit, but it's not shown over here.
Yeah, then there needs to be separate output saying that I cannot represent its value given the
number of bits.
So you should be careful what you do with this output.
Makes sense, right?
In real chips, there are a lot of conditions where you get that sort of thing.
But in this case, we're just starting, so we don't have that output.
Very good question.
OK, so this is 1 implementation.
Again, I'll let you study it on your own, but let's take a look at some examples over here.
Somebody again designed this.
You could also design it.
You know, one way of designing it a terrible way.
But it's a possible way, assuming you're automated, is construct the truth Table 2 N bits and then
basically this.
This function has two n + 3 inputs, right in terms of number of bits and the output is N That's a
huge truth table if N is large.
So you can do that, you can do sum of product form and you can try to minimise that.
Not a good idea here.
You can also do it based on logical thinking, dividing it into components.
So divide and conquer.
That's also a very principled method of designing.
So essentially you divide and conquer here.
For example, somebody divided functions.
You have an adder over here, right?
You use the adder to do addition or subtraction.
If you use Two's complement notation, which you will see when you actually do the exercises,
addition and subtraction are the same.
Essentially, when you add A&B, you do A+B.
If you want to subtract B from a, you need to take a bitwise complement of B and do add it to over
here with a carrier.
I'll let you think about that.
Also, again, you'll do exercise on this one, but essentially this F2 over here, one of the bits of
the function determines whether you do addition or subtraction or some of these other functions.
So based on the value of F2 you decide which whether you use the inverted B or non inverted B.
And you can see that if F2 is 1, you use the inverted B over here you use another inverted B and to
do the subtraction you do actually another inverted B over here.
Hopefully that's clear.
If for example, the output of the ALU selects this one, let's let's select something different
selects this one.
If F1 and zero are 00.
If one and zero are the bottom 2 bits, 00.
So it's just this case and this case you do either A&B or A&B bar, right?
So I can analyse the circuit.
So which one's A and BA?
OK, yeah, A is connected to here.
And if F2 is 0, you get A&B because B is connected to here.
So you get A&B as you can see bitwise and if F2 is equal to 1, you get B bar at the output of this
multiplexer.
And B bar goes here and a goes here.
And you do A&B bar.
And if one and 0, if they're both 0, the the, the this multiplexer selects this output over this
input over here, which is assigned the value 00 over here, as you can see.
So you get the functions that you want A&B or A&B bar based on the value of F2.
So I just analysed some of the how, how the circuit operates, right?
Based on what we have seen so far, we've seen all of the components over here, multiplexer selects
which input to pass to the output based on these values.
There's another multiplexer over here that selects which input to use internally in the ALU that
determines the output eventually, right?
So you can see that the the F or function select inputs determine the outputs in the end, and you
need to Add all of the other circuitry that you need over here.
So there's a zero extension over here.
That means you extend if you don't have enough bits as a result of the Lu function, you extend it
with zeros.
We'll see some of these later on also, but it's good for you to study this on your own and you'll
see some exercises when we put the in the in the exercise sessions.
Yes.
Why is this more efficient than having having individual units for each operation?
Yeah, that's a great question.
Basically, why is it more efficient?
In the end, you need to make some selection, right?
Whenever you actually, let's say want to do some operation on 2/2 inputs A&B, you need to make some
selection.
This could be more efficient so that you can actually control things using a single F function,
right?
But your, I think your point is very well taken in the sense that you could actually have complete
different units and do the selection outside, right?
The reason why we do it this way is usually it will aid modular design.
So if you set, this is my ALU, these are my functions, and I'm not going to change that.
You can take this ALU and stamp it out on your machine, right?
Whereas if you had to design everything individually, separately, without having this universal
concept of the ALU that could be replicated, it could be worse for design.
Hopefully that makes sense, right?
It eases design.
Nine in the end, that's why we go up this modular level.
This is our ALU, this is what it does.
And at some point, people don't care how it's implemented.
OK, OK, so I'll let you study this thing, OK.
There are more combinational blocks that we're not going to talk about, but again, you can read more
about it and you're going to do some of this in your labs.
Also, let's talk about tri-state buffer.
This is something that's conceptually very nice implementation wise.
You need to be careful on how to actually make it work, but I like talking about it because it's
actually a nice way of thinking about how things operate.
So essentially it's a very simple logic circuit.
It enables gating of different signals onto a wire.
What does this mean?
The wire is Y, The input is A.
There are two inputs, A and E E is the enable input.
If E IS0A doesn't get connected to Y.
So you can see that Z, there's Z over here that's floating if E IS1Y takes the value of A.
So this way you can decide whether or not to connect something to an output wire, which is Y.
So floating signal, signal that's not driven by any circuit.
We've seen that before when we talked about CMOS.
It's open circuit floating wire.
It's not necessarily bad if you're not going to use Y for something else or if something else is
going to drive Y, it's OK.
It's bad if you use the Z value without driving it.
Then you may get some garbage value because you don't know what value is there, right?
What voltage is there?
OK, it tries to state buffer, acts like a switch.
It's kind of like a transistor, but it's, it has an enable signal, right?
It's not exactly like a transistor if you think about it.
OK, so basically why is this useful?
Imagine a wire connecting the CPU and memory.
At any time, only the CPU or the memory can place a value on the wire, but not both, because either
the CPU is going to communicate to the memory some bit, or the memory is going to communicate to
the CPU some bit, right?
You can add 2 tri-state buffers, 1 driven by the CPU and the other by the memory and ensure at most
one is enabled at any time, right?
I'll go, I'll show you the picture.
Basically, you're going to see this picture later on.
These are huge blocks that consists of many, many other blocks internally.
I'm not showing any of that, but they're communicating with each other using this bus or a set of
wires, let's say.
And at any point, if CPU wants to communicate to the memory, the the input is not shown over here,
but in the next slide, I'm going to show it.
CPU basically sets the gate CPU signal to one or something, sets the gate CPU signal to 1 so that
the output over here is loaded on this bus and gate memory signal is set to 0 so that memory
doesn't load or put some value on the bus.
And if the memory wants to commit to the CPU, you do you.
Vice versa.
OK, if both of them are enabled, then you're in trouble.
You may get a short circuit, right?
We don't want that.
OK, so this is a more, let's say realistic or full example from your book.
If the processor wants to put something on the bus, this enable signal is set to 1 and all of the
other enable signals should be set to 0 so that you don't get a wrong bad value, multiple things
driving the bus and all of the other components can see the value on the bus.
This is not a tri-state buffer.
This is just a buffer to amplify the signal.
This way other components can communicate with other components, right by setting the enable signals
appropriately.
OK, we're going to see more of this.
You can also design other things like multiplexer using tri-state buffers.
This is a multiplexer 2 to 1 multiplexer using tri-state buffers.
Remember we design and this is a 4 to 1 multiplexer using tri-state buffers.
Remember we designed the multiplexer.
This was the four to one multiplexer using and gates which are more expensive potentially.
Now we can actually design a multiplexer in a cheaper way using this component called tri-state
buffer.
And you can you can take a look at this, right?
So for example, these, this is a trash state buffer.
There's another tri-state buffer, T0T1.
If S is 0, this tri-state buffer is disabled.
Yeah, I guess if if S is 0, this tri-state buffer is enabled.
Sorry, because there's a inversion over here.
Y becomes D0.
If S is 1, this is your books kind of drawing.
This is S Also, if S is one, this tri-state buffer is enabled.
This tri-state buffer is disabled.
So Y becomes T1.
That's essentially A selector, right?
And it can do the same thing with four tri-state buffers that are connected using a combination of
not connected that are controlled using a combination of these select signals.
OK, so that's the four to one multiplexer.
So digging deeper, I'm not going to cover this actually because this is again one level below the
abstraction.
What's the difference between an inverter and a tri-state buffer?
You need more transistors basically if you want to dig deeper.
How is the tri-state buffer constructed?
You can see that there's an enable signal that turns off the connections or turns on the
connections.
OK, So we covered essentially a lot of combinational blocks so far.
We're not completely done, but I'm going to take a break over here.
Essentially, what we're going to do is we're going to do a very quick tour of logic simplification.
We're going to cover priority circuit, etcetera.
And then in the remaining part of the lecture, we're going to go to sequential logic.
So let's take a break until the bell rings, and then we'll continue.
All right, let's get started.
The spell is very flaky, or maybe it's my ears.
It's always an issue.
And is it the input or is it the sensor that's the problem, Right?
I think the input is also weak here and the sensor may be also weak.
That combination doesn't work very well.
OK, so now we've covered a lot of blocks in the last two lectures.
Let's see some more.
So you've seen this actually.
So I'll go through this relatively quickly, but I'll introduce a couple of interesting circuits or
interesting concepts to minimise things more easily.
So this was our full ladder in SOP form logic expensive.
And if you want to simplify it, you can use boolean simplification rules and you can see that this
can be simplified to the sum bits can be simplified to three input XOR and the output the carry out
can be simplified to three input majority function.
OK, the the more general question is how do we simplify boolean logic and how do we automate it?
Essentially the original Boolean expression, whatever you're thrown at, certainly the sum of
products form may not be optimal in terms of number of terms or number of logic gates.
And we're not even talking about latency right now, but latency usually has some good correspondence
with the number of gates.
Energy also has some good correspondence with number of gates.
So the first order thing to do is really get rid of as many gates as possible instead of having
redundant gates.
OK, so this is one made-up cooked up function.
The key is basically, how do we reduce this, right?
And this is the function that is equivalent to.
Clearly, I would like to implement only this A+B or A or B in this case.
So the goal of logic simplification is to reduce the number of gates and inputs as much as possible
and also reduce the implementation costs and later latency and power and energy.
So this is basically, this is the basis of what automated design tools are doing today.
And I'll give you a glimpse of how they operate in general.
They're they're essentially based on this uniting theorem, which is a fancy word for eliminating
variables, right?
So we have systematic techniques for simplification that are amenable to automation.
And a key tool is this uniting theorem.
So if you look over here, what uniting theorem states is you find the onset of a function.
Basically onset is where the output is 1, meaning if in this case the output is 1 and you try to
find variables that change when the function value is 1.
So you find that A's value does not change within the onset rows, but B's value changes, meaning the
functions output is independent of B's value rate.
Hopefully that makes sense.
If an input can change without changing the output, that input value is not needed.
And this is the key of uniting theorem.
If you hear uniting theorem, that's basically what it is.
So this way you can eliminate B&A remains.
OK, so you look at the onset first, you don't care about the offset.
I mean you can also look at your offset only and not the onset.
That's another SOP versus POS, right?
And you eliminate variables that change when the function output doesn't change.
OK, similarly, and then you can also of course do the simplification using Boolean logic and satisfy
show show that you actually have done the right thing.
OK.
Similarly, you can see over here that for the onset rows, these value does not change.
But as value changes, so I can eliminate B and the function is really B bar.
Oh, sorry, B's value stays the same but A's value chain.
So you can eliminate A so the function's value is B bar.
Hopefully that makes sense and it can generalise us to any number of inputs and outputs.
And this is also the basis of graphical optimisations that I will talk about, but I will not go into
detail as we will see.
So essentially you can keep doing this and eliminate variables.
You find two element subsets of the onset where only one variable changes its value.
The single variable can be eliminated.
And you can do this using equations or using graphics.
OK, let's let's take a look at an example.
What does this mean?
Like a function's value doesn't change, but a variable changes.
That means you don't care about that variable, right?
So we represent this using don't cares in the truth table.
And these are very useful for minimising things, so I'll give you an example of a priority circuit.
Inputs are requesters with some priority levels.
These are hard coded priorities.
Output is a grand signal for each requester.
So you may be requesting a bus for example, right.
We've seen the bus earlier.
You have the CPU, you have the memory, you have the video, you have the storage or Ethernet.
They're all requesters and they are granted access to put something on the bus or the wire.
So let's say an example of a four bit priority circuit.
With that you have 4 requesters A3A2A1A0 and you have 4 outputs over here that could control the
tri-state buffers that enable loading of a value from a given requester to the bus.
And this is our truth table.
You have 4 inputs, 4 outputs, and there's a static priority, meaning that if a three requests the
bus, it has the highest priority Y-3, which is the bits corresponding to the to that particular
requester is 1.
Everybody else's bits corresponding bit is 0.
Meaning if a three requests the bus requests the bus, then it gets the bus, it has the highest
priority.
Now if a three doesn't request the bus and A2 requests the bus, let's say it's memory, then it gets
the bus and nobody else gets the bus.
Now if neither A3 nor A2 request the bus, but A1 request the bus, it gets the bus, not a zero.
And I guess you got the hang of it.
A zero has the lowest priority and if no one requests the bus, no one gets the bus.
Sounds good right?
Now this is an expensive representation of the truth table.
We could have easily represented it with don't cares this smaller representation of the truth table.
So basically let's look at the highest priority.
X means I don't care what the value of this input is.
So if a three is 1, I don't care of the values of.
I don't care about the values of.
A 2A1A0Y3 is 1 and Y2Y1Y0 are all zeros.
If a three is 0 and a two is 1, I don't care about the values of A1A0.
This is the output and you get the rest of it hopefully.
So this is a very simplified representation and this way by simplifying the truth table using Dawn
cares, you can generate A minimal circuit.
So you can see this is the implementation of this, right?
So Y 3 is directly connected to a three, Y 2 is equal to a three bar and a two and you get the rest
of it also sounds good, right?
So this is another way of minimising circuits.
There are many ways as you can see.
And this is essentially uniting theorem in action.
What we did actually was the uniting theorem without really going through the mechanical aspects of
it.
We use the logical way of thinking, right?
Basically, we kind of united all of these to access because we know that the output doesn't depend
on these, right?
OK, say it again.
Sorry, this is not a decoder, basically decoder, sorry.
Remember what decoder is, It has an M bit input and it has two to the north outputs.
Right here we have N bit inputs and N outputs, OK.
We're not detecting a pattern.
We're basically giving priority based on some assumption that we made in terms of the priority of
the circuits.
Good question.
OK, so there's another way of simplifying circuits which I'm not going to go into.
This is probably the most fun, but sorry, we don't have time.
This is not used in minimisation, but they actually you use the uniting theorem.
This is a pictorial way of minimising circuits by visualising opportunities for simplification.
I'll let you uncover the suspense.
We're not going to cover them in this course.
OK, If you're interested in earlier incarnations of this course, we covered them, but we decided
they're more interesting and important things to cover for you to be prepared for the future.
But if you want to have some fun, you can do it.
OK, that brings us to the end of Combination Logic.
Actually.
Any questions?
You guys asked a lot of questions.
That's good.
Let's keep this interactive.
There's a question over there.
No, they're fun.
I mean, test is fun also, but we're not covering them.
Although there could be very good questions to be asked in carnival maps.
I'm not going to do that.
OK, OK, so let's talk about sequential logic.
No other questions.
Going once, twice.
So now everybody knows how to design combinational things, which is good.
And you'll do a lot of this, don't worry.
You'll do this in exercises, you'll do this in labs.
So you're going to be experts in combinational logic design.
Maybe not the fastest adder design or multiplier design, but if you're interested, you can actually
learn about that also.
But now let's talk about more powerful circuits.
So far, what we have seen is something that cannot remember, right?
And without memory you cannot do much essentially.
So we're going to start sequential logic finish is pretty aggressive, so probably we're going to
finish it tomorrow and tomorrow.
We're going to do other things also tomorrow and next week, not just tomorrow.
OK, so basically what is sequential logic?
Sequential logic is essentially circuits that can store information and do more things with it.
We're going to look at how to store information.
First we're going to start with cross coupled inverter and then we're going to talk about basic
concepts to design sequential circuits like state clock, talk about asynchronous versus
synchronous.
And then we're going to get into designing finite state machines.
Probably we're not going to get into it today, but maybe to the beginning of it we'll get to these
are some readings more specific to what I'm going to cover in this lecture.
So sequential logic over here, but then there are other things over here also, as we will cover next
week.
So I should say that this is really important because if you don't have memory, if you cannot store
information, no computer can work.
I think no human can work also, at least work well, let's say.
So here I show you an example.
Most of this is actually memory.
I'll give you some more examples.
So this thing is the processing chip.
Most of it is what we call SRAM, static random access memory.
And then there's something called DRAM that occupies a lot of space.
That's a lot of space as you can see.
And then there's something called storage salt state drive.
So most of what we do is memory actually.
And inside this thing a lot, most of what we do is also memory.
So this was 1995 Pentium Pro.
We're going to look at the basic principles of this in lecture 16 or so, multiple basic principles
and are building up to this lecture.
So you can see that there's a processor chip, a lot of memory in there and there's a cache chip, a
lot of memory in there.
That was a lot of SRAM, and over time, because we could put more transistors on a single chip, the
processor chip started dewaring all of this caches and it became a lot of caches internally.
We're going to talk about the concept of caching also.
So this was Pentium 4 with a lot of memory inside.
We're not even talking about the memory.
So if you look at this picture, a lot of the regular structures are just memory, and we will see why
they're regular soon.
OK, this is AMD and most of it is memory over here.
The green part, there's more memory that I'm not highlighting, and people are adding more memory.
People are putting more memory.
One chip on top of another chip, and that's chip that you put on top of the processor chip is
essentially all memory.
This is IBM, their big powerful chip in 2020.
A lot of memory.
This is a GPUA lot of memory.
OK, I could keep doing this, but it becomes boring at some point, you know?
So this thing is also a lot of memory.
So how do we build this memory, right?
We're going to talk about dense memory later, but let's start with the basics of memory.
So essentially combinational circuits only output depends only on current inputs.
It doesn't remember.
We want circuits that produce output depending on current and past input values.
That's essentially what memory is, past input values.
You remember the past so that you can do something with it.
The question is, how can we design A circuit that stores information?
So this is the definition of a sequential circuit.
Combinational circuits are part of it, but you also have memory in it, some storage element
essentially that enables you to remember what happened in the past.
So what is that storage element?
So you need to capture what's happened in the past, meaning you need to capture data.
And capturing data starts with capturing one bit of information.
How do we capture one bit?
There are many ways of doing it, but we're going to start with a way that's based on what we've
learnt so far.
We've learnt about inverters and inverter inverts.
If you actually have two inverters whose outputs are connected to each other's inputs, then you
capture data.
This is called a cross coupled inverter.
It looks like this.
It may look scary or weird, but there's nothing weird in it.
It's a logic circuit in the end and you know how these operate.
Inverter 1.
Inverter 2.
Inverter one's output is connected to inverter 2's input.
Inverter 2's input is connected to inverter one's input.
Inverter 2's output is connected inverter one's input, and we'll call this Q, this output Q, and
this output Q bar.
So this has two stable states.
Q is equal to 1.
Or Q is equal to 0, right?
Sounds good.
Do you agree?
Say it again.
What comes in?
That's a great question.
We're going to answer that.
How do you actually enable those stable states?
This is kind of useless.
Who sets Q to one or zero?
That's what you're asking basically and that's a great question.
So there's also, before I go into that, there's also another state, actually it's called metastable
with both outputs oscillating between zero and one.
If you somehow try to force, we don't know how to do that yet, Q&Q bar to be equal.
The circuits goes a bit crazy because of its analog characteristics that we're going to cover next
week in timing and verification.
Basically it doesn't, it cannot decide easily what to store one or zero.
Eventually there could be a random way of storing one or zero.
So you don't want the situation basically.
So there are two stable states.
You always want to be in one of the stable states.
Q is equal to 1, Q bar is equal to 0, or Q is equal to 0 and Q bar is equal to 1.
OK, but we've stored information somehow.
But your question remains.
It's kind of useless without a control mechanism for setting Q.
So now we're going to add that control mechanism.
But we start with this because this is the basic circuit that can capture data.
If you don't have a mechanism for setting queue, you deal with whatever queue was there.
But that's not what we want.
OK, so more realistic storage elements have a control mechanism for setting queue.
We will see the Rs latch soon.
But before I go into this, I'll create a bit of suspense.
Let's look at SRAM.
So this is actually all of the caches that is inside your processors.
More than 80% of your chip is SRAM.
It looks like this.
There is your cross coupled inverter.
Basically most of what we have on a chip today is cross coupled inverters on a processor chip.
And there's a setting mechanism that I'm not going to talk about right now and resetting mechanism,
which is these transistors over here.
We're going to talk about those later.
This is one way of setting and resetting.
You can input data from here and from here to the SRAM cell, OK, But it is a cross coupled inverter.
OK, We will get back to SRAM and later DRAM, which is an even denser storage.
Later on today we're going to cover latches and flip flops.
So these are actually very fast.
You can access them in parallel, but very expensive.
You're going to see that one bit is going to cost us 10s of transistors with two cross coupled
inverters.
You know that each inverter is 2 transistors.
We have 4 transistors.
Even that's expensive compared to DRAM or flash with static RAM, SRAM it's relatively fast, not as
fast as latches and flip flops.
It's more expensive one bit cost 6 plus transistors.
In this particular case you have 2246 transistors.
As you can see, if you want to make it more robust and faster, you may need 8 etcetera.
Dynamic RAM, slower reading, destroys content, needs special process for manufacturing.
That's why you cannot put it on your chip as caches usually.
But it's very cheap.
We will see that one bit costs only one transistor plus one capacitor later on.
And then there's other storage technology.
This is main memory essentially, and we will see that later in lecture 20 plus.
And then there's other storage technology like flash memory, which has enabled all of us to take
pictures indiscriminately, right, or videos.
And they get stored in this arrays of flash memory that's inside here.
The reason I can have this is because of flash memory actually, and it's extremely cheap, but it's
much slower access takes a long time.
But as the one characteristic that none of these other ones have, which is it's non volatile.
If you turn off the power, meaning all of the power rails don't provide power, you still keep the
bit stored over there.
You don't lose the bit.
OK, so we may talk about that later on, but so this lecture we're going to focus on the expensive
fast things.
Sounds good, yes.
Yeah.
Well, it depends on what it is like.
If it's called SSD sold state drives, then they're flash memory.
If it's called HDD hard disk, then it's magnetic memory.
And then there's tape.
You know, people, do people know about tape here?
OK, tapes.
There are also tapes that are much slower, but they actually are very dense information.
There's also cd-roms, DVDs, etcetera.
Those are all other storage technology over here.
OK, let's start with the Rs.
This slide, so we'll, we'll basically make this cross coupled inverter work, meaning we want to be
able to set it and reset it.
And I'm going to make them into a cross coupled NAND gates.
Your book talks about cross coupled NOR gates.
It's essentially the same.
You know that NAND and NOR can be interchangeable based on logic equations, right?
So this is my an other weird structure right now.
I have some parts of the cross coupled inverter and the section inverter in the end accepted as two
inputs NAND and two control inputs S&R.
By setting SNR appropriately I can store one or zero in Q.
So these are cross coupled NAND gates.
As I said you could do it with NOR gates.
Also data stored at Q inverse is always at Q bar.
S&R are control inputs.
In idle states, both S&R are held at one.
Meaning if S is 1 and R is 1, Q is captured and Q bar is captured and they stay the same, right?
You can convince yourself of that because if S is 1, the output of this NAND gate depends on Q bar.
The output of this NAND gate depends on Q only, right?
And this becomes Q bar.
This becomes Q.
Now if you want to set this, you drive S to 0.
If you set this one to zero, and at the same time R is 1, S IS0R is 1, then what happens is this
becomes one and this is 1 and this is one.
This becomes zero and this becomes one.
This keeps becoming one.
This keeps becoming 0, right?
Hopefully that's clear.
So if you want to set Q to 1, you drive S to 0 while keeping R at one.
OK.
If you want to drive set Q to 0 while keeping S at 1, you drive R to 0.
And the exact opposite thing happens.
If R is 0 this is 1, and one one this is 0, right?
Makes sense.
So that's why it's called set reset.
Setting S to 0 enables output to be 1.
Setting R to 0 resets the output.
OK, so we SNR should not be both 0 at the same time.
We'll see this more in the timing lecture.
Your book does something different.
It basically gives a value, but we're going to forbid it because it's bad practice to actually have
these to be one at the same time or to be 0 at the same time.
So basically, if R&S are one, the output conserves its previous value, whatever was stored there.
If you want to store A1, you set S TO0R to 1.
If you want to store a zero, you set R to zero and S to 1.
And you basically avoid setting both RNS to 0, driving both RNS to 0 at the same time.
OK, why not RNS 0?
There are two reasons for it.
One is principle, the other is practice.
It's good to have two things supporting it.
Principle means if RNS are both 0Q and Q bar are both 1.
And based on my principles, Q&Q bar should not be one at the same time, right?
So I broke my invariant that I set out that I should maintain.
Whenever I'm breaking my invariant, I'm probably doing something bad.
OK, so that's principle.
Practice is a little bit more convoluted.
Meaning let's assume that if SNR transition back to one at the same time, you somehow set SNR to 0.
These became one and they transition back to one at the same time.
Q&Q bar begin to oscillate between 1 and 0 because it's not clear what the result should be, right?
What do you think?
Because you're driving these were one, OK, these were one.
These were zero.
And you set both of them to one at the same time.
Now 11, this is 0, this becomes zero and one one, this is 0, this becomes zero.
Also, we broke our invariant.
That's why this is happening.
And who wins?
It depends on how fast each of the gates is.
It depends on some random fluctuations that happen in the circuit.
It depends on your voltage temperature.
Who knows?
This can be a random number generator.
OK, so because you broke your variant, this happens.
This is called method stability in circuits, and we don't want that.
So in the timing lecture, we're going to see more of this.
Stay tuned.
But we're going to forbid that for now.
Yes, You have a question.
So that you don't run into.
The second situation, OK, yeah, but that's how it is.
You know, for this to make sense that invariant is necessary, right?
Think about it, is there any other ways you do nor gates and you'll run to the opposite situation.
Try to get out of it.
It's going to be difficult.
OK, very good question Things.
So OK, this thing is not nice in the sense that you forbid things and people do it right.
Forbidden fruit is good to eat.
So we need some way of ensuring people don't do this right?
And that's what brings us to gated D latch and more expensive hardware.
OK, this is gated D latch coming.
Basically, the designer says, how do I guarantee that someone will not screw up and set both of them
to 0, right?
Well, this is how we guarantee that.
Add another two NAND gates, more expensive.
But this guarantees that nobody can set S&R to 0 at the same time, right?
Let's go back.
Yeah, this is forbidden.
Now nobody will be able to do it.
OK, let's take a look at how this operates when so we have a bit this input called right enable that
goes to both of these NAND gates over here and a data input.
So a single data input.
If right enable is set to 1, Q should take the value of data input and Q bar should take the value
of data bar D bar.
If right enable is set to 0, nothing should change in the circuit, meaning Q&Q bar should have their
old values.
And this beautiful circuit also ensures that SNR can never be 0 at the same time.
Because if right neighbor is 1, this is D bar and this is D bar bar which is D If right neighbor is
0, this is 1 and this is one right.
So now we guarantee that that terrible situation doesn't happen and nobody can screw up.
Sounds good.
So that's the gated D latch.
This is the truth table.
Basically.
I told you the truth table.
You could actually simplify it.
If right neighbor is 0, I don't care about DD is XQ is equal to Q previous.
If right neighbor is 1, output is D Makes sense, right?
OK, great.
So now we have something that works.
It's a lot of gates.
You can, well, it's 4 gates.
It's 16 transistors, more than 16 actually, because there's an inversion over there, 20 transistors
or 1818 transistors I think.
But it works expensive.
OK, now let's build a wider things with this register.
Basically, this is a very simple concept.
If you store 1 bit, this is 1 bit.
If you want to store more bits, you put them in parallel, use more D latches.
So this way you can have a four bit register.
For example you can have 4 inputs that are supplied in parallel D0 to D3 and four outputs that are
coming out.
And you usually you you may or may not need Q bar right?
That may not be part of what you provide.
So if you have a single write enabled signal for all latches for simultaneous writes.
So if you want to store always a four bit value, you connect the right enable signals of the D
latches to a single right enable control signal.
So basically a structure that stores more than one bit and can be read from and written to.
It holds 4 bits and it's data is referenced as Q30.
This is a notation.
You will see more of this notation when you do Verilogue programming, which we will talk about
either tomorrow or next week or both.
So this is an array kind of notation.
It's a four bit array, 4 bit register actually, and it's could be specified this way.
Basically it's abstracted now.
I don't care how it's implemented.
It has a right enable bit, it has a four bit data input.
It has four bits Q output, and if right enable is 1, Q gets D If right enable IS0Q stores whatever
was stored here in the previous time, right?
OK, Q outputs whatever was stored.
So that's the register.
Now let's put it in memory.
Memory is actually multiple registers, which you can address separately using a decoder and you can
read from using a multiplexer.
Basically, we'll use a decoder multiplexer combination to address memory and get the data out of it.
It's a set of multiple.
Registers that are addressable.
But before I go into it, let me give you the example that we're going to build.
So basically memory is comprised of locations that can be written to a read from an example memory
area with four locations.
Let's say we have 4 addresses, 2 bit address 00011011.
It may be containing this sort of data.
Every unique equation in memory is indexed with a unique address.
So 4 locations require 2 address bits, 32 locations require 5 address bits.
Log N Essentially, addressability is the number of bits of information stored in each location.
In this particular case, 8 bits are stored in each location.
So you need an 8 bit register in each location, and you have four of these 8 bit registers.
And the entire set of unique location and memory is referred to as the address space.
In this particular case, you have 4 locations where each location is 8 bits.
So a total memory is 32 bits.
Typical memory is a much larger billions of locations.
We're going to build that in lecture 20 plus, but let's take a look at the toy memories first.
So let's implement a simple memory array.
Not even go to 8 bits, but 8 bits is easy actually, with three bit addressability, meaning each
address contains 3 bits of information, each location contains 3 bits of information, and address
space size of 2.
Meaning you have only two locations.
You have only two locations, each of them stores 3 bits.
You can think of it as two registers, each of them storing 3 bits.
So total memory size is 6 bits.
So we're going to start with our gated D latch that nobody can screw up by setting RNS to 0 because
they don't even know what RNS is.
It's not exposed to them.
That's good.
This is our six bit memory array.
We're going to basically replicate this latch inside there.
So let's take a look at reading first.
Not even writing, forget about write enable.
How can we select an address to read?
Because there are two addresses.
The address size is log 21 bit basically.
So these are our D latches.
Now I added a decoder.
This is a 2A1 to two decoder.
You have one bit address, you have two lines.
If address is 0, the top register is enabled.
If address is 1, the bottom register is enabled, right?
So we call this the word line and some parts bit lines as you will see later.
But this is the address decoder.
Actually you didn't see this was a one to two decoder.
We looked at 2:00 to 4:00 decoder.
But one to two decoder is actually a simplified form of two to four decoder.
We'll see the two to four decoder soon when we build a larger memory.
And this is a multiplexer essentially together with the decoder which provides a select input.
So what does this do?
This thing selects whether this output, this bit at the top comes from this registers top bit, or
this registers top bit based on the address.
So if address is 0, this output this becomes one.
This output determines the output of the OR gate because this is zero.
Wait a second, this is 0, Sorry, this is zero.
So the output of this becomes 0.
Meaning none of these things over here are enabled because all of these multiplexer selects are 0 if
the address is 0.
If address is 0, I'm reading from the top three bits.
If the address is 1, I'm reading from the bottom 3 bits.
OK, so together with an address decoder and a multiplexer, I can read from these D latches.
Sounds good right?
This is beautiful.
Now you've seen the basics of memory.
All memory operates this way.
It's an array structure.
Internally these things may be different, but now we have D latches.
So remember this was the multiplexer or selector that we had.
OK, let's talk about writing to memory.
We're going to construct the full thing.
So how can we select an address and write to it?
Basically, we have the right enable bits.
So instead of having just the decoder, we also have the right enable bits over here.
Sorry.
So if the address is 0 and right enable bit is 1, then this input.
So what I've done is basically we, I added the right enable bits.
I also added the data inputs which were not here.
If you remember, there's a memory that you cannot store anything into.
There's a memory with really the gated D latches right now with the data inputs coming in.
So if if address is 0, this becomes one.
If the right enable bit is one, this whole line becomes one.
Meaning this the entire right enable bit going into 3 registers or three gated D latches in this
particular case, and all the data values get input.
Data 2 gets input here, data one gets input here, data 0 gets input here.
If address is 1 and right enable is 1, then the data value that's supplied from somewhere outside
the structure gets input.
To the three bit register over here if addresses don't care.
So if address if, if, if right enable is 0, you read.
If right enable is 1, you write right.
Makes sense.
So you need to set the right enable to 1 so that you can write the data inputs coming to a
particular address you select.
Hopefully that's clear.
OK, so that's writing.
So if you want to put in put it all together.
If you enable reading and writing from a memory array that looks like this now.
So here for example, if you if I this, I didn't, I didn't show you the reading circuitry over here
because I just wanted to write.
But if you want both, you need to have the address decoder over here and you need to have the
multiplexer to read, but you also have the circuitry to write.
So by combining the circuitry to write data and also read data, you can do both writes and reads to
this particular memory that consists of two locations where each location stores 3 bits.
Hopefully makes sense.
OK if you want to expand this, what you do is you add more rows.
So if this is a 2 entry memory, 2 location, or two address memory with three bits stored in each
address.
Let's say we want to have four addresses where each location can store 3 bits.
You basically have 4 rows and we have 3 columns because we didn't expand the columns.
Yes, three different values.
OK, so tell me what data you want to store 100.
OK, so if you want to store 100 to the first row, you set the this, this input to 1, this input to
0, this input to 0 that's external.
You set the address to 0 and you set the right enable to 1.
If you do that, this word, this right enable will be all one and the values 100 based on the
operation of the gated D latch will go into the latch will go into the queue of that latch.
OK, and nothing will happen here because right neighbor is 1 but address is 0.
So there will be nothing written over here.
OK, now you will also be at the same time reading from here.
But that's how the circuit is constructed.
That's fine, right?
Maybe you ignore that output.
OK, very good question.
So this is the extended circuit, a bigger memory array.
We have 4 locations, each location is 3 bits as you can see over here.
So what do you do?
You have a bigger array, you have a bigger decoder.
Now you've actually seen this decoder.
This is a 2 to 4 decoder.
Because we have 4 locations, we have two address bits, and you can see that this thing is a 2 to 4
decoder.
If address 1000, this is 1.
Otherwise, this if address 10 is 01, this is 1.
If it's 10, this is 1.
If this is 11, this line is 1.
So that's the decoder, right?
That's the operational decoder.
We detect the pattern.
Depending on the value of the pattern, we enable one line coming out of the decoder and that enables
us to decide which row of three bits or which register.
We read from right or write into right depending on write enable signal.
And we also make the multiplexers wider such that you can select it's a four to one multiplexer.
You can see this or gate.
It has four inputs based on the address you select to read either from here or here or here or here,
right?
Hopefully that's clear.
I'll let you study it on your own if it's not fully clear.
But these are actually based on every principle that we use so far to build a multiplexer decoder
and the gated D latch.
And this is a working memory.
And your book provides an example over here, for example, reading location 3.
Let's go through this relatively quickly.
You set the address bits to 11.
You set the right enabled bit to 0 because we don't want to write, we want to read.
So these inputs are essentially useless because you're not writing, you're reading.
So if the added bits are one one the decoder, this bit is, this line is enabled.
All of these lines are disabled and these are the.
So this is 1.
And whatever value was stored here, it seems like it's 1:01.
That's gets output 101.
Makes sense, right?
So you read the value that's stored over here, which is the output of these gated D latches.
OK.
So I'll let you study this on your own.
But what we've used over here is the gated D latch which we have just seen, the decoder which we've
just seen, well, which we have seen.
In the past lecture and a four to one multiplexer, we've exactly used the two to four decoder and
four to one multiplexer.
OK, questions.
Can you please go back?
Yes, here.
So there are three multiplexers.
So it's better to look at over here because I clearly show that.
So this is 1 multiplexer over here.
Basically what you're trying to do is you're trying to read 1 bit from a particular location, right?
And there are four possible locations.
You need to select one of those.
And how do you select, You decoded the address and the address enables the select input of the
multiplexer.
Makes sense, right?
So this is 1 multiplexer over here that decides which D2 to read.
Do you read the D2 of address 00, address 01, address 10 or address 11?
And how this happens is there is a or gate that has four inputs.
1 is coming from the output.
Let's say we're reading from the top address over here.
So address 00.
This is this becomes one because of this decoder, right?
This is 1 and all of these are 0.
So these and gates all evaluate to 0 and the result of this or gate is what is coming from this
register.
OK or D Yeah, D latch.
I cannot, I cannot hear you, Sir.
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
Decoder is the decoder is decodes the address and it also serves that the select input of the
multiplexer.
What you said is true actually.
OK, OK, I will do on a site which is implementing logic functions using memory.
That's actually very interesting.
So for example, if you store particular bits, you can actually implement the truth table.
Memory arrays can also perform boolean logic functions.
So this is an AND function based on the address.
You can actually store particular bits, zeros and ones.
Something is happening here.
Let's hide that.
So you can implement an and bit by storing 0001 respectively in addresses 00011011.
So whenever you access memory with a value which is treated as an address, you can get the output
that's corresponding to the function which is stored in the location that's associated with the
inputs.
So inputs are A&B which are actually addresses to the memory and the output is what's stored in the
memory.
So you can implement the function that's very similar to look up tables that we have seen.
So essentially 2 of the M location M bit memory can perform AN input M output function.
So memory array is used to perform logic functions.
So each address is a row in the truth table.
Each database is the corresponding output value.
So as I said, look up tables are commonly used in FPGA.
This is from your book.
I'm not going to talk about this here, but you will see this more in the FPGA programming and
lectures.
Let me introduce sequential logic circuits and then we're going to stop.
Essentially, we've examined designs of circuit elements that can store information.
Right now, we will use these elements to build circuits that can remember past inputs.
So I like this analogy.
This is a combinational lock.
How many people have used this one?
OK, This doesn't remember what you've done in the past, right?
It's purely combinational.
But this is a sequential lock.
How many people have used this one?
OK, some fewer people.
This is more secure, potentially.
I think I'm going to stop here because I'm not going to cover the concept of state at the moment.
I'll see you tomorrow.